Guide to the American College for Girls records,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series 1: Records of the Trustees
  - Subseries I.5: Records Relating to Land Acquisition
    - Peet's statements (in the form of a detailed account) of the purchase of Arnavutköy property, 1907-1908 (Box 9, Folder 6-7)
    - Peet's correspondence, 1912 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - "American College for Girls at Constantinople The Story of the Purchase of the Property at Arnautkeuy for the College Site," by Peet (bound ms.), 1912 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence between trustees and Mrs. Alexandrian re purchase of her property, 1902-1903 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - American College Land Fund in account with Peet, 1904-1910 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence and memos pertaining to acquisition of land at Arnavutköy, 1905-1906 (Box 9, Folder 12-13)
    - Correspondence to Borden and trustees from Patrick re acquisition of land at Arnavutköy, 1907 (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - Materials pertaining to acquisition of Arnavutköy property (includes chronology prepared by Borden), 1907 (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - Action of Executive Committee on transfer of Uskudar property. Correspondence to Woman's Mission Board, 1908-1909 (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - Copies of correspondence pertaining to acquisition of Arnavutköy property (includes Patrick's memorial sent to Roosevelt prior to conference), 1908 (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - General correspondence pertaining to land acquisition (includes an account of meeting between Roosevelt and American delegation), 1908 (Box 10, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence re negotiations between U.S. and Turkey for purchase of Arnavutköyproperty, 1908-1912 (Box 10, Folder 19-20)
    - Correspondence to Patrick and Dutton from Peet re Greek claim to Arnavutköy property, 1912-1914 (Box 10, Folder 21)
    - Alexandrian file: correspondence re claim on college property, 1922-1925 (Box 10, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence re Musurus Property, Arnavutkoy, 1917-1946 (Box 10, Folder 23-24)
    - Correspondence re property tax and war damage claims, 1913-1938 (Box 10, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence and memos re "Tract A" property, Arnavutkoy, 1922-1933 (Box 10, Folder 26)
    - Correspondence re property (Arnavutkoy) connected with college, 1920-1930 (Box 10, Folder 27)
  - Subseries I.6: The Committee on Instruction, 1905-1924
    In the absence of extensive faculty records, the trustees' Committee on Instruction has useful material including various proposals to expand the curriculum by adding an education department, a medical department, and an agricultural program. There is considerable correspondence concerning the hiring of teachers, courses offered, and the scholarly propensities of the faculty.
    Samuel Train Dutton of Columbia University served as chairman from 1903-1919. After his death, his successor was Talcott Williams, also of Columbia. Both men carried on an extensive correspondence with Mary Patrick and each played a significant role in the other activities of the Board of Trustees.
    - Correspondence Patrick/Dutton, 1903-1919 (Box 11, Folder 1-16)
    - Correspondence to Dutton from Borden and Hart Borden, 1910-1912 (Box 11, Folder 17-18)
    - General correspondence to Dutton from Borden, 1914-1917 (Box 12, Folder 19-22)
    - General correspondence to Dutton, 1911-1919 (Box 12, Folder 23-24)
    - General correspondence to Williams, 1917-1922 (Box 12, Folder 25-27)
    - Correspondence to Williams from Patrick, 1912-1924 (Box 12, Folder 28-30)
    - Correspondence to Williams from Olmstead, 1919-1924 (Box 12, Folder 31-34)
    - Reports prepared by Williams, 1917-1923 (Box 12, Folder 35)
    - Report to Williams (includes alumnae list), 1922 (Box 12, Folder 36)
  - Subseries I.7: The Committee on Finance, 1907-1933
    The Committee on Finance was under the direction of George Plimpton from 1907-1932. In addition to the usual financial records there is correspondence that details the difficulties involved in keeping the college open during World War I. Patrick pays tribute to the efforts of U.S. Ambassador Henry Morgenthau in helping the College cope with wartime pressures. Also included here is Patrick's postwar article entitled "Fourteen reasons for an American Mandatory over Turkey."
    - Correspondence to George Plimpton, chairman of the Committee on Finance from Patrick, 1907-1912 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Copies of Plimpton's correspondence to Patrick and Borden, 1909-1912 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence to Plimpton from Patrick, 1913 (Box 13, Folder 3-7)
    - Copies of Plimpton's correspondence to Patrick, 1914-1919 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence to Plimpton from Patrick, 1920 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Copies of Plimpton's correspondence to Patrick, 1920 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence to Plimpton from Patrick, 1921-1922 (Box 13, Folder 11-12)
    - Copies of Plimpton's correspondence to Patrick, 1921 (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence to Plimpton from Patrick, 1923 (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - Copies of Plimpton's correspondence to Patrick, 1923 (Box 13, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence to Plimpton from Patrick, 192-1933 (Box 13, Folder 16-17)
    - Copies of Plimpton's correspondence to Patrick, 1930-1933 (Box 13, Folder 18)
    - General correspondence to Plimpton, 1905-1914 (Box 13, Folder 19-22)
    - Copies of Plimpton's correspondence, 1907-1914 (Box 13, Folder 23-24)
    - General correspondence to Plimpton, 1915 (Box 14, Folder 25)
    - Copies of Plimpton's correspondence, 1915 (Box 14, Folder 26)
    - General correspondence to Plimpton, 1916 (Box 14, Folder 27)
    - Copies of Plimpton's correspondence, 1916 (Box 14, Folder 28)
    - General correspondence to Plimpton, 1917-1919 (Box 14, Folder 29-33)
    - Copies of Plimpton's correspondence, 1919 (Box 14, Folder 34)
    - General correspondence to Plimpton, 1920 (Box 14, Folder 35)
    - Copies of Plimpton's correspondence, 1920 (Box 14, Folder 36)
    - General correspondence to Plimpton, 1921 (Box 14, Folder 37)
    - Copies of Plimpton's correspondence, 1921 (Box 14, Folder 38)
    - General correspondence to Plimpton, 1922 (Box 14, Folder 39)
    - General correspondence to Plimpton, 1923 (Box 14, Folder 40)
    - Copies of Plimpton's correspondence, 1923-1924 (Box 14, Folder 41)
    - General correspondence to Plimpton, 1924-1925 (Box 14, Folder 42)
    - Correspondence Plimpton/Adams, 1924-1930 (Box 14, Folder 43)
    - General correspondence to Plimpton, 1927 (Box 14, Folder 44)
    - General correspondence to Plimpton, 1930 (Box 14, Folder 45)
    - Copies of Plimpton's correspondence, 1930 (Box 14, Folder 46)
    - General correspondence to Plimpton 1932 (Box 14, Folder 47)
    - Copies of Plimpton's correspondence 1932 (Box 14, Folder 48)
    - Correspondence Plimpton/Staub 1932 (Box 14, Folder 49)
  - Subseries I.8: The Building Committee, 1908-1921
    Designs and layouts for buildings at the Arnavutköy campus can be found in these records. The chairmen of this committee, Albert Wiley and later Walter B. Walker, each made occasional visits to Istanbul allowing them to view the results of their committee's labors. There is an address by Walker at the dedication of Gould Hall.
    - Summary Report, "Action of the Trustees in the Matter of Layout and Buildings", 1908-1910 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence to Charles Rutan from Patrick, 1908-1909 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - General correspondence to Albert Wiley, chairman, Building Committee, 1911-1914 (Box 15, Folder 3-4)
    - General correspondence Walker, 1914-1920 (Box 15, Folder 5-15)
    - General correspondence Walker, 1920-1921 (Box 16, Folder 16-20)
    - Correspondence to Walker re Otis Elevator, 1921 (Box 16, Folder 20a)
    - Address by Walker "On the Occasion of the Dedication of the Administration Building" (Gould Hall), [no date] (Box 16, Folder 21)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence re Building Committee, 1909-1912 (Box 16, Folder 22)
    - Building Committee Record Book (Bound volume with minutes and reports), 1914-1921 (Box 16, Folder 23)
    - Reports and minutes of Building Committee's meetings (bound volume), 1910-1913 (Box 16a, Folder 24)
    - Building Committee reports, 1913-1916 (Box 16a, Folder 25)
    - Building Committee; miscellaneous correspondence (includes estimates of building costs), 1910-1914 (Box 16a, Folder 26)
  - Subseries I.9: The Committee on Medical Education
    The attempt to establish a medical school forms a particularly interesting chapter in the pioneering efforts of ACG. The suffering produced by World War I highlighted the need for modern medical facilities and under Mary Patrick's leadership, funds were raised to build and equip a medical school for women in 1923. But the cost of operating the facility combined with the new government regulations reserving professional education to Turkish institutions compelled the closing of the medical school in 1924. The records of the Committee on Medical Education reflect the dream and the initial implementation of that vision. The chairman of the committee was Edward Haskell who served from 1919-1924.
    - Committee on Medical Education; minutes of Medical Committee, 1818-1922 (Box 16a, Folder 27)
    - Estimated budget, Bingham Medical Building, 1922-1923 (Box 16a, Folder 28)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence re expenses, 1922-1923 (Box 16a, Folder 29-30)
    - Reports issued by the Medical Committee, 1919-1924 (Box 16a, Folder 31)
    - Report of the Medical Department for the second semester, 19231-1924 (Box 16a, Folder 32)
    - Medical Department; general, includes student transcripts, 1920-1923 (Box 16a, Folder 33)
    - Committee on Medical Education; includes publications re American Hospital, 1920 (Box 16a, Folder 34)
    - Committee on Medical Education; includes correspondence re the American Hospital, reports of the American School for Nurses, and summary data for in-patient and out-patient departments, 1920-1922 (Box 16a, Folder 35-37)
    - Correspondence Haskell/Olmstead, 1919-1922 (Box 17, Folder 38-42)
    - Correspondence Haskell/Olmstead, 1923-1924 (Box 17, Folder 43-46)
    - General correspondence to Haskell, 1919-1922 (Box 17, Folder 47-50)
    - Correspondence between Olmstead and Lester Briggle, assistant treasurer, 1923-1924 (Box 18, Folder 51-54)
    - Correspondence to Haskell from Alden R. Hoover, 1919-1923 (Box 18, Folder 55)
    - General correspondence to Haskell, 1922-1923 (Box 18, Folder 56-59)
    - American Red Cross; copies of Livingston Ferrand's correspondence; chairman, Central Committee, 1920 (Box 18, Folder 60)
    - Correspondence to Haskell from Harold Keyes, secretary, Committee on Medical Education, 1919-1923 (Box 18, Folder 61)
    - General correspondence to Keyes, 1920-1923 (Box 18, Folder 62)
    - Copies of Haskell's correspondence to Hoover, 1920-1921 (Box 18, Folder 63)
    - Copies of Hoover's correspondence, 1920-1921 (Box 18, Folder 64)
    - Correspondence to Haskell from William Bingham, 1920-1923 (Box 18, Folder 65)
    - Copies of Haskell's correspondence to Bingham, 1919-1923 (Box 18, Folder 66)
    - General correspondence to Bingham, 1920-1923 (Box 18, Folder 67)
    - Copies of Haskell's general correspondence, 1919-1923 (Box 18, Folder 68)
    - Copies of Haskell's correspondence to Patrick, 1919-1923 (Box 18, Folder 69-70)
  - Subseries I.10: General
    Jane Page: correspondence regarding the merger proposal of ACG and RC
    - Jane Page: correspondence re merger proposal of ACG and RC Boards of Trustees and endowment funds, 1956-1958 (Box 18, Folder 71)
- Series II: Records of the President
  - Subseries II.1: Annual Reports
    The Annual Reports provide a valuable summary of the growth and evolution of ACG. After 1889-90 they generally appear in printed form. The format varies but many contain such information as a list of faculty, a summary of the academic year, reports from the departments, names and residences of the students, and a list of gifts to the college including names of donors.
    For some years there is a separate printed "calendar" or catalog which includes admissions requirements, course listings, and information about the career and location of graduates.
    The quality and breadth of the reports improve with the years; the later ones contain fuller information as well as appended lists and addenda. Some make mention of local or national affairs. The reports of 1894-95 and 1896-97 provide information about political unrest; the report of 1910-11 stresses the threat of a cholera epidemic. During the years of the Balkan Wars (1912-14) and World War I, President Patrick discusses the mood and conditions in Istanbul as well as the difficulties faced by the college. During the 1920s, the reports chronicle a period of growth for the college.
    From 1932 on, there was one president for both Robert College and ACG and thus one report was prepared covering both institutions. Generally, each includes a dean's report that speaks more specifically about ACG's faculty and curriculum. There is also information about the activities of the students. In the absence of extensive faculty records, appended committee and departmental reports are particularly useful.
    - Annual Report of the President, 1889-1812 (Box 19, Folder 1-12)
    - Annual Reports of the President, 1912-1921 (refer to 1918-1919 Annual Report for events from 1917) (Box 20, Folder 13-18)
    - Annual Report of the President 1921-1934 (Box 21, Folder 18-27a)
    - Report of the Dean 1927-1928 (Box 21, Folder 23)
    - Annual Reports of the President, 1935-1947 (Box 22, Folder 28-36)
    - Joint Reports submitted to the Trustees, 1947-1949 (Box 22, Folder 37-37a)
    - Condensed Annual Report, 1949-1950 (Box 22, Folder 38)
    - Annual Report of Dr. Elizabeth B. Stanton, American vice president and dean of the faculty, 1950-1951 (Box 22, Folder 39)
    - Annual Report of the President, 1951-1955 (Box 22, Folder 40-42)
    - Summary Report for ACG (Duncan Ballantine), 1956 (Box 22, Folder 43)
    - Report, "A Comparison of ACG with American and Turkish Schools," (Ballantine), 1958 (For annual reports from 1959 to 1963 see Robert College Series 3, Box 28) (Box 22, Folder 44)
  - Subseries II.2: Correspondence
    Mary Mills Patrick's files contain only a small proportion of her voluminous correspondence. There are only a few copies of her own letters in this series. Fortunately, however, many originals may be found in the trustees series, and the administrative files of the New York Office. The presidential files consist largely of incoming letters from many colleagues and friends. These concern college affairs primarily, but other events as well. Some were sent to Dr. Patrick on her trips to Europe and the United States, and contain news about Turkey. For example, Roxana Vivian, acting president writes about her visit to parliament during the civil unrest in April 1909 (Box 23, Folder 7). There are letters (frequently copies) from Henry Morgenthau, Oscar S. Straus, Talcott Williams, and Albert Bushnell Hart. There are also a few letters from former students, and a folder of correspondence (copies) with the writers unidentified.
    Dr. Patrick's concerted efforts to establish a medical school are well documented in these files. Finally, there is an address by Dr. Elsa P. Kimball at the memorial service for Dr. Patrick held in Canterbury, New Hampshire, June 30,1940.
    Note: There is an additional box of Mary Patrick's correspondence located at the Hoover Institution, Stanford University, Palo Alto, California. Materials deal with the period of World War I.
    - General correspondence to Patrick, 1895, 1898 (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence Patrick/Robert Thomson re religious status of college (See reports to trustees/Stanwood, Box 1, for additional correspondence on this issue), 1904 (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Paper read by Patrick at memorial service for Clara Hamlin Lee, 1902 (Box 23, Folder 2a)
    - General correspondence to trustees from Patrick, 1903-1924 (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence to Patrick from Peet, 1917, 1922 (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence to Patrick from the field secretary, 1919 (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence to Patrick from Borden, 1915 (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - General correspondence to Patrick, 1904-1929 (Box 23, Folder 7-9)
    - Correspondence to Patrick (unidentified), 1905-1923 (Box 23, Folder 10)
    - Patrick address: "The Significance of the Conference of the World's Student Christian Federation", 1911 (Box 23, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence to Patrick re shipment of possessions at time of her retirement, 1924 (Box 23, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence Patrick/Staub, 1922-1935 (Box 23, Folder 13-17)
    - Correspondence to the Medical Education Committee from Patrick, 1919-1924 (Box 23, Folder 18)
    - Address given at Memorial Service for Patrick, 1940 (Box 23, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence to Adams, 1924-1932 (Box 23, Folder 20)
- Series III: Records of the Dean
  There are seven folders of dean's records. Three cover the period of Louise B. Wallace's deanship, mainly the period 1914-1919. Subjects relate primarily to the difficulties involved in bringing over new faculty in the light of wartime conditions.
  Eleanor Burns became dean in 1924 and in 1932 received the added responsibilities of American vice president when the two colleges were merged. She served until her retirement in 1950. Earlier she held positions as registrar and professor of physics. Much of her correspondence can be found in the records of the New York Office. In the Dean's files there is an account of a memorial assembly held at the college following her death in 1952.
  - Correspondence to Louise B. Wallace, 1914-1919 (Box 23, Folder 21-23)
  - Correspondence to Wright from Burns, 1937, 1943 (Box 23, Folder 24)
  - Copies of Burns's general correspondence, 1920-1947 (Box 23, Folder 25)
  - General correspondence to Burns, 1916-1926 (Box 23, Folder 26)
  - Memorial Assembly for Burns, 1952 (Box 23, Folder 27)
- Series IV: Records of the Secretary and Bursar
  These records deal with administrative and financial matters, but many transactions between the college campus and the New York Office were directly affected by policies of the Turkish Government. Finances were complicated by the fact that tuition rates had to be adjusted to fluctuations of the Turkish lira. Faculty salaries were affected by conditions during World War I, particularly when the Turkish Government imposed a personal tax on college personnel in April 1915.
  Mary Patrick's letters to Susan Olmstead, secretary and bursar, while largely administrative, are sprinkled with comments about life at the college as well as about events in Turkey. Patrick's fundraising trips to the United States also involve correspondence with the New York Office. She continued to be active in raising funds after her retirement in 1924 and thus continued to correspond through 1926. The records contain information on teachers' salaries, currency rates, scholarship awards, and travel arrangements.
  Kathryn Adams, Patrick's successor, writes about the effect of Ataturk's reforms. For example, the college was asked not to distinguish any longer among the nationalities of the Republic when identifying students, unless their legal residence was outside Turkey. The Government also required that the teaching of the Greek and Armenian languages be dropped.
  Adams also kept Olmstead informed as to how new faculty members adjusted to life at ACG, along with writing about the difficulties involved in filling the places of longtime members of the faculty who retired. Olmstead in turn reported to Adams regarding decisions by the trustees and the state of financial support.
  - Correspondence to Olmstead from Patrick, 1912 (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence Olmstead/Patrick, 1915-1924 (Box 24, Folder 2-15)
  - Correspondence Olmstead/Patrick, 1925-1926 (Box 25, Folder 16-17)
  - Correspondence Olmstead/Burns, 1916-1930 (Box 25, Folder 18-32)
  - Correspondence Olmstead/Adams, 1924 (Box 25, Folder 33-34)
  - Correspondence Olmstead/Adams, 1926-1927 (Box 26, Folder 35-45)
  - Correspondence Olmstead/Marion Talbot, acting president, 1927-1928 (Box 26, Folder 46-47)
  - Correspondence Olmstead/Adams, 1928-1930 (Box 26, Folder 48-55)
  - Correspondence from Olmstead to Walker re fundraising trip to the United States, 1913 (Box 27, Folder 56)
  - General correspondence to Olmstead, 1914-1924 (Box 27, Folder 57-60)
  - Olmstead; general, 1925 (Box 27, Folder 61)
  - Correspondence to Olmstead from Briggle, 1922 (Box 27, Folder 62)
  - Copies of Olmstead's correspondence to Williams, chairman, Instruction Committee, 1919- 1920 (Box 27, Folder 63-64)
  - Correspondence between Olmstead and William S. Murray, 1919-1925 (Box 27, Folder 65-66)
  - Copies of Olmstead's correspondence to Elizabeth Ingersoll, field secretary, 1919 (Box 27, Folder 67)
  - Correspondence Olmstead/Professor Isabel Dodd, 1919-1926 (Box 27, Folder 68-69)
  - Correspondence Olmstead/Wallace, 1914-1929 (Box 27, Folder 70-78)
- Series V: Records of the Office of the Faculty
  The faculty records are fragmentary. There were meetings of the faculty and committees of the faculty, but apparently very few documents remain. There is a report of a 1909 faculty meeting and a folder of memos addressed to the "Educational Committee" regarding candidates for faculty appointment (1919-20). In addition, there is a proposal for a Home Economics Department (1920), a faculty handbook (1927) and some correspondence between individual faculty members and the New York Office. Finally, this series contains a mimeographed faculty, staff and community directory, dated 1961-1962.
  - Faculty
    - Resolution re Ida W. Prime, 1919 (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence re officers of administration and instruction, 1908-1909 (Box 28, Folder 2)
    - Summary report of a faculty committee meeting, 1909 (Box 28, Folder 3)
    - General; faculty applications4 (Box 28, Folder 4)
    - Proposed plan for a Home Economics Department (Box 28, Folder 5)
    - Pamphlet titled "Information, Regulations and Suggestions for Instructors in the Constantinople Woman's College", 1927 (Box 28, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence Hall (chemistry teacher)/Olmstead, 1916-1924 (Box 28, Folder 7)
    - Claim of Paul M. Flory in legal suit against the college, 1939 (Box 28, Folder 8)
    - Faculty, staff and community directory, 1961-1962 (Box 28, Folder 9)
  - Records of the Students
    - Diary written by Penka Racheva (one of the first Bulgarians to study in the Horne School), 1882-1883 (Box 28, Folder 10)
    - One-page description of the Student Government Association at ACG, 1905 (Box 28, Folder 11)
    - Booklet written by students titled "Echoes of the New Ottoman Constitution" [1908] (Box 28, Folder 12)
    - Booklet titled "History of the Constantinople 1930 College Self-Government" Records of the Alumnae, 1930 (Box 28, Folder 13)
    - List of graduates with biographies, 1898-1899 (Box 28, Folder 14)
    - List of graduates who taught in mission schools, 1899 (Box 28, Folder 15)
    - List of graduates [early 1900s] (Box 28, Folder 16)
    - Alumnae Association report, 1913 (Box 28, Folder 16a)
    - Associate Alumnae minutes, 1911-1916 (Box 28, Folder 17)
    - Constantinople College Association--meeting reports, 1916 (Box 28, Folder 18)
    - Constantinople College Association--notices of meeings, 1915-1917 (Box 28, Folder 19)
    - Material relating to Halide Edib, 1908-1946 (Box 28, Folder 20)
- Series VI: Records of the Office of the Trustees, New York